hi everybody welcome back to the channel
if you voted in our YouTube poll about
the next video then you'll be not so
surprised to know that this one is about
the ice cream calculator dream Scoops
ice cream calculator to be more specific
so if you want to know how to use one
stick around and I'll talk you through
it
okay so here we go dream Scoops ice
cream calculator this is an online ice
cream calculator you don't have to
download it to anything you can just pop
online and do it and it will help you
balance out your recipes to make sure
that all your ice creams turn out
really nice so let's get the computer
loaded up share the screen and show you
what we're doing
and here we go this is where you are
going here so I'll put this link in the
description below and this will be the
page that opens up to you it's you know
a nice little intro it's good website
actually if um if you want some some
light reading for ice cream anyway you
know you can redo this if you want I
know how it works we'll scroll down and
here we go this is the ice cream
calculator itself there's some
predetermined numbers in here that we're
going to change but in the back end all
of these cells have calculations
attached to them that means when you put
in the numbers of all your ingredients
you'll get some totals down here and it
will also tell you how much of your ice
cream you're going to end up with it'll
give you some basic details about pack
and relative sweetness but if I'm honest
I don't find those particularly accurate
obviously that's where Patrick's ice
cream calculator comes in I will do
another video on that because a lot of
people wanted that it appears so
let's get started we're going to create
a deep chocolate ice cream with a
chocolate olive oil strachatella it
sounds good
so first we're going to do is double
click each cell and change it the
percentage to our milk fat so we're
going to use two percent milk here I'm
going to click on I'm on Apple so it's
returned but click enter whatever you
want to call it and then it will drop
down to your cream we're going to use 33
fat Lucerne cream by the way just in
case you haven't seen like other
Canadian cream videos
you can just keep pressing enter or
return and go back down to the cocoa
powder fat percentage we're going to use
Ghirardelli so thank God it's not
Hershey's
Ghirardelli is around 16 fat so she's
16.6 so let's put that in
and here we go this is the area of the
website we put in the numbers so we're
going to start with some known entities
and see where we get so again I'm just
pressing enter here and it'll drop down
to the next box you don't have to type
anything at that point other than the
numbers that you want in there okay so
we're going to put in 300 grams of milk
300 grams of cream 110 grams of sugar
let's put in 20 grams of dextrose
we're not going to put in the
maltodextrin I don't like that and we're
not going to put any invert sugar in
this we're not going to put honey corn
syrup condensed milk no skim milk powder
yes we're going to put in some let's put
a starting figure of 40 grams in there
we're also going to put in
20 I don't know five grams of cocoa
powder we're also going to put in a
little bit of stabilizer so we've now
got some xanthan gum incredibly
expensive over here
these are our basic numbers
okay so we're at 13 13.7 fat 10.4 milk
soil is non-fat 16.4 sugar and 43.3
total solids okay so 10.4 I'm just going
to drop a couple of grams
of that
10.2 that's not too bad
um
yeah 25 grams of cocoa hey look that
that's not a that's not a bad little mix
there if you scroll down you can see
what they recommend
12 to 14 fat for for luxury which is
North America yes
um super premium 14 to 18. if you've got
an 18 fat using Canadian cream you're
gonna struggle it's just gonna be greasy
horribleness so stick in the premium ice
cream and use better ingredients that
will bring you into the Super premium
level okay 40 to 42 total solids 43 I
like it a tiny little bit higher
um super premium 14 to 17 sugar where
it's 16.4 nice see here it recommends
zero point
two percent
stabilizer now we've got
793 grams total mixture okay so if we
really wanted to put the right amount to
0.1 percent stabilized for xanthan gum
remember xanthan gum is quite a strong
single level stabilizer
I wouldn't want to put in 0.2 percent
so 0.2 percent being 1.4 grams is a lot
so I'm going to put in
one whole gram
of xanthan gum okay I won't do anything
really to the to the recipe
but this is what we've got okay we've
got a pack 22.7 relative sweetness 15.7
and that relative sweetness relates to
this here this line here so we've got
110 grams sure 20 grams of dextrose
remember dextrose isn't as sweet as
sucrose
um it also is really really good at
depressing the freezing point so it
makes it much more scoopable than a
solid block of whatever that you buy in
your stores
and that is where we are going to stop I
think this is where we're going to keep
our recipe 300 300 110 20 grams of
dextrose 38 skim milk powder and 25 a
cocoa with one
Soul lonely gram of xanthan gum
all right let's get those in the pan
warmed up get everything dissolved and
then we can get it in the fridge
I couldn't wait any longer for
my scale so I went out and bought some
these are straight from Canadian Tire
nice and cheap
but it really really helps when making
ice cream because you need these exact
numbers to create a perfect ice cream
you can't just wing it with cups and
hope for the best so scales is the way
to go Plus
I'm from England
we use scales grams all that kind of
jazz so
get our milk and cream out and let's get
started so we're going to bring the
recipe
up on the screen
so we went for 300 milk
oh
300 milk okay
exactly 300. I can't tilt it and show
you but it is
and we're looking at
300 of cream
nice and easy to do when you've got
scales there's no messing around
no
washing up cups while you're
there we go perfect washing up cups
while you're in the middle of creating a
recipe no thanks no thank you sugar
haven't got the sugar
[Applause]
noise
right sugar 110
grams
let's get this in
it's a bit slow this
cheaper scale so we're just going to
give it time to catch up
there we go 110.
20 grams of dextrose going in here
we're gonna
tear again
and use a spoon
20 grams of dextrose nice
I think more and more people in North
America are using grams these days but
use whatever works for you I'm not going
to tell you what to do
38 grams of skim milk powder
38 grams I might go for a bigger spoon
here
we go 38 grams of skim milk powder and
finally
we've got
our beautiful
Ghirardelli this is Dutch
cocoa
I've got some nice stuff coming over
which is really good just placed another
order for some cocoa Berry Brut which is
really really nice cocoa powder here
with 25 grams of our cocoa powder smells
good
so I've got a delivery coming
I've always got deliveries coming moving
country 25
moving country surprising how much stuff
you have to buy
25 grams
nice
what is it this time
furniture
[Applause]
I have got tips if you're moving country
if you're interested in oh my God why
can't I get this close back up
nope I'll do that in a minute right
that's it we're going to get this on hob
and start warming it up gently
okey-doke
as always nice slow stirs just warm this
up we're not really trying to do
anything crazy you do want to bloom
cocoa powder though it's blooming it's
just a fancy word just to say warm it up
essentially what you're doing is you're
bringing the fats the cocoa fat out of
the powder and distributing that
properly
because if you're interested or not
cocoa powder never actually truly
dissolves on an atomic level it just
breaks up into its individual little
elements and floats around in your
liquid
[Music]
um
and when you see like a nice chalky
milkshake or something and it starts to
separate
that's what that is that is your cocoa
powder in your drinking chocolate or if
you're just using Cocoa Brown itself
it's the solid particles sinking back
down because they're not dissolved and
then when you whisk it back up they will
re-emulsify temporarily into the liquid
and then you've got what you think is a
nicely dissolved cocoa powder anyway
I'll stop yammering on and get this up
to temperature and sit it there for a
couple of minutes let that xantham gun
do its thing and then we'll get it in a
container into the fridge
um
[Laughter]
interestingly enough
Ghirardelli cocoa powder doesn't
dissolve or you know disperse quite as
easily as Hershey's so at least her
shoes have done something right their
cocobana the rest is crap
but um anyway we're up temperature let's
get it in
let's get it in this noisy Bowl straight
into the fridge
good Oak now we've got our chocolate
chilled down if you use cocoa powder and
it doesn't completely dissolve in the
fridge you'll see little black spots
dark spots and that is the last little
few bits of cocoa powder just they've
you know kind of dissolved somewhat into
your base just give them a quick stir if
they really don't dissolve then you can
either just run it through a fine mesh
sieve or take a spoon and just to you
know take off the top but these are all
completely gone in the base nicely now
just put it in the machine and when
we're near completion we're gonna get
our chocolate olive oil stretch teller
mix ready so
let's get moving on
so whilst that's finishing off we're
gonna get our chocolate this is
for Walmart Sarah
finest
range 72 percent
Coco let's break some of this up
we're going to put it in a tiny little
jar
[Music]
this is the Olive Oil we're using extra
virgin olive oil you've got to use extra
virgin you've got to use real olive oil
because if you use a blend of oil then
it very well may not freeze because some
oils don't so I've decanted some offices
what we use for cooking strange enough
we're just going to put a touch
in there
like so that's
approximately 15 to 20 grams
gonna put that in the microwave short
little stints until it's melted and
we'll Stir It Together
[Music]
okay
last you want to take it if you use the
microwave you want to take it out just
before it all melts so whilst there's
still a couple of small little pieces in
there and then Stir It
the last 10 15 20 seconds to make sure
those last bits are melting without
burning your chocolate you shouldn't
burn it with the oil in you can use
coconut oil if you want
any any oil you like the flavor of but
it needs to be able to set so here we go
ice cream is ready
pour this in
last few seconds
turn the compressor off
again just to repeat we do that so you
turn the freezer off on your machine if
you can that is
um
to make it easier to remove from the
machine
on the
muzo or the lilamuzo machines
that's kind of one of their nice little
features you can turn that Chiller down
and then give it a minute or two to
churn and you can scuba that nice and
easy
into the freezer
tomorrow
foreign
and here we go it's been in the freezer
overnight and
I'm quite excited to try this one
see you look at the top it looks good
texture looks good consistency looks
good no weeping no ice no nothing that
tells you that a recipe is good balanced
and
oh I can see all the bits of chocolate
in there too yes
let's
go
that
oh hell yeah
rich chocolate
Ghirardelli can't go wrong with its
American brand
um
smooth really nice flavor
it's not bitter and disgusting like
Hershey's
it's got this warm chocolate feeling
would I imagine this would be good for
hot chocolate but
no fatty greasy film
the chocolate straticella
stretchy attella
it's got this um it's not
olive oil forward
comes in at the end after you've eaten
the ice cream the chocolate's gone then
you get this
this waft of of olive come through
it's really nice
it's really
it's really subtle yeah it kind of warms
the back of your throat a little bit
it's really really nice
mmm
action
can't stop eating it
so
there we go
a quick lesson in dream Scoops ice cream
calculator I'll do this again
periodically
so people can start to get used to using
it you can download that
spreadsheet to your computer
if you choose to and then you don't have
to be online to use it
if you want to know how to do that let
me know and I will show you
but overall
a perfect chocolate ice cream with a
incredibly
good chocolate stratocella with olive
oil throughout loads of that in there as
well
I tell ya
that has been a journey coming over here
trying to get the ice cream right
but we're there so
I am looking forward to lots of
different ice cream makes I got a huge
list as well loads of things gone up
just put a poll up on YouTube last week
it's quite clear what people want to see
but every two weeks I will put a poll up
on
YouTube you can vote for one of four
options of what you want to see me make
and then
I will just get on and make it I will
probably make the other ones as well you
know because that's just me but I'd like
to thank all of my Kofi supporters I'll
put a little list up here so you can see
those that have chosen to support the
channel so if you fancy supporting the
channel you can head over to Kofi I will
put a link on the screen here and it
will also be in the description
if you offer support it just helps me
make the recipes that you want to see so
thank you ever so much for subscribing
and nice look we got loads of more
subscribers coming on board now we're
like 3100
so we're getting some good guns let's
see if we can get to 4 000 subscribers
by the end of the year that would be
amazing and
bye
[Music]
oh